Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
poetry ca. 40 Linear Feet ca. 650 Items
Duke University David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University 411 Chapel Drive Box 90185 Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
This catalog is a revised and enriched document based upon the original created by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University, and obtained by the Walt Whitman Archive. The original papers and catalogue records are held at the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Access Restrictions:
Collection is open for research.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Scope and Content
The bulk of Duke University's Walt Whitman holdings were acquired through a series of substantial donations made by Dr. and Mrs. Josiah C. Trent, from whom the Trent Collection of Whitmaniana takes its name. Much of the Trent material was originally gathered by Richard Maurice Bucke, Whitman's friend and literary executor, who sold manuscript versions of his biography of Whitman, along with his collection of unpublished letters and Whitman's personal papers and books, in London in 1935. The next year, Jacob Schwartz offered for sale in New York a large portion of the Whitman holdings that had belonged to Bucke, and many of the items listed in the catalogue of this sale were a part of the original donation made to Duke by Dr. and Mrs. Trent in 1942. The Trent family made several important additions to their initial bequest in the years following the establishment of the collection, but Duke University does not expect its Whitman manuscript holdings to expand at any time in the near future.
The Trent Collection of Whitmaniana incorporates material spanning the dates 1841-1947, with the bulk of the material dated 1845-1849, 1854-1857, and 1864-1892. The virtual reorganization of the collection, based upon that devised by Ellen F. Frey in A Bibliography of Walt Whitman (1945; rpt. Port Washington, NY: Kennikat Press, 1965), divides it into six series: Correspondence, Writings, Clippings, Material About or Relating to Whitman, Portraits, and Miscellany.
Although the Trent Collection contains a wide variety of Whitman material, this catalog deals only with those items deemed poetry or prose manuscripts.
Biographical Information
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892—Manuscripts; Poets, American—19th century
Item List
- [a nation announcing itself], about 1856; duk.00030; xxx.00221; xxx.00110; MS 4to 14; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript draft of the opening passage of Poem of Many in One, Leaves of Grass ( 1856 ). The final title of the poem, By Blue Ontario's Shore, first appeared in the 1881/1882 edition of Leaves. On the verso is both prose and verse beginning "Asia" that appears to be a draft of Salut Au Monde!, a poem first published as Poem of Salutation in the 1856 edition of Leaves.
- Carols Closing Sixty-Nine, about 1888; duk.00056; xxx.00310; MS 4to 20; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript of suggestions for the title of a collection of poetry which eventually appeared under the heading Sands at Seventy in the 1888 volume of poetry and prose entitled November Boughs. The title Carols Closing Sixty-Nine appears here as one of the possible names for this collection. The verso of this document contains the underlined words "Sands at Seventy" and a cancelled note reading "for annex to the preced," which corresponds to ideas expressed on the recto.
- [The Great Laws do not treasure chips], about 1855; duk.00264; xxx.00271; xxx.00250; MS 4to 9; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  This manuscript contains lines which, after revision, appeared in the eleventh poem in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass, later titled Who Learns My Lesson Complete? On the verso are cancelled lines, beginning "hands are cut," which later appeared, in a revised form, in Faces, which was originally published as the sixth untitled poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- [Great are the myths], about 1855; duk.00259; xxx.00430; MS 4to 10; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  This manuscript has a partially cancelled draft of the first lines of Great Are the Myths. The poem Great Are the Myths was published first, untitled, in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass as the concluding poem, and again in the 1856 edition as Poem of a Few Greatnesses. The poem went through many revisions through the different editions of Leaves of Grass, then was permanently dropped in 1881–1882, except the two couplets that became the poem Youth, Day, Old Age, and Night. The verso of the manuscript has cancelled prose beginning "The true friends of the Sabbath."
- [You lusty and graceflu youth!], between 1850 and 1855; duk.00032; xxx.00430; xxx.00266; MS 4to 11; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  An early version of a part of Great Are the Myths, a poem published first, untitled, in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass as the concluding poem, and again in the 1856 edition as Poem of a Few Greatnesses. The poem went through many revisions through the different editions of Leaves of Grass. then was permanently dropped in 1881–1882, except the two couplets that became the poem Youth, Day, Old Age, and Night. On the verso is partially cancelled verse beginning "Are the prostitutes nothing?" which is a draft of lines from the third poem in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass, ultimately called To Think of Time.
- [And now I care not to], about 1860; duk.00031; xxx.00071; MS 4to 195; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  This manuscript is an early draft of a portion of the poem that became In Paths Untrodden, which was published first in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. The verso contains a list of thirteen suggestions for titles or groups of poems, including "The States," "Prairies," "Prairie Spaces" and "Prairie Babes." In Paths Untrodden opens the Calamus group in all editions of Leaves of Grass, taking the title in 1867.
- Leaves of Grass, about 1881; duk.00053; xxx.00001; MS 19; poetry 18 leaves handwritten
  The handwritten Table of Contents of the 1881-1882 edition of Leaves of Grass with instructions to the printer. Also included is a proof of the title-page of the same edition, with Whitman's corrections.
- Leaves of Grass, about 1881; duk.00098; xxx.00001; I-1; poetry 270 leaves handwritten
  Printer's copy for portions of the 1881-1882 edition of Leaves of Grass containing manuscript and printed pages with numerous corrections, additions, and instructions to the printer. A lock of Whitman's hair, enclosed in a wrapper, also appears with this collection.
- Poem of Materials, about 1860; duk.00042; xxx.00281; xxx.00047; MS 12mo 15; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  This manuscript contains notes for poetry, including phrases which appear in section 6 of the final version of Starting from Paumanok and in Mediums. The published version of Mediums, originally Chants Democratic No. 16 in the 1860–1861 edition of Leaves of Grass, later appeared as part of Passage to India ( 1871–1872 ), and finally in the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves of Grass. Starting from Paumanok was published first in the 1860–1861 edition of Leaves of Grass as Proto-Leaf. The verso is a prose fragment dealing with political independence that contains phrases and ideas similar to those found in Whitman's complete but unpublished essay The Eighteenth Presidency!
- [Theme for piece], about 1869; duk.00045; xxx.00272; xxx.00262; MS 4to 22; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  An outline for a poem on various types of music, potentially related to Proud Music of the Storm and/or The Mystic Trumpeter. The poem The Mystic Trumpeter was first published in The Kansas Magazine of February 1872. Proud Music of the Storm was first published in the Atlantic Monthly in February 1869. The verso contains cancelled notes about a stanza to describe a triumphal instrumental and vocal chorus corresponding to that of man triumphing over temptation and weakness.
- [?Gliding], 1870; duk.00022; xxx.00235; II-5 17; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A fragment describing street and interior scenes similar to those in Outlines for a Tomb. Outlines for a Tomb was first published in The Galaxy in January 1870 under the title Brother of All, with Generous Hand, and finally in 1881 under the title Outlines for a Tomb.
- [All that we are], undated; duk.00023; xxx.00788; xxx.00614; II-5 21; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Draft of fifteen lines of poetry, first published only after Whitman's death in Notes and Fragments ( 1899 ). The last three lines on this manuscript leaf appear in another version in a long manuscript, Pictures, which probably dates to before 1855 and is held at the Beinecke Library, Yale.
- Proud Music of the Storm, about 1869; duk.00046; xxx.00262; MS 4to 23; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Correction notes and potential extra lines for the poem Proud Music of the Storm, first published in The Atlantic Monthly ( February 1869 ) as Proud Music of the Sea-Storm. Subsequently, the poem was titled Proud Music of the Storm in Passage to India ( 1871 ), Two Rivulets ( 1876 ), and in Leaves of Grass ( 1881-1882 ). The verso contains the beginning of a letter on Attorney General's Office stationery.
- [it is no miracle now that], about 1855; duk.00007; xxx.00048; MS 4to 3; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript draft of ideas about touch related to sections 28-30 in the final version of Song of Myself. The verso contains prose writing related to ideas expressed in Leaves of Grass, as well as lines which would appear in a slightly altered form in what became section 4 of Song of Myself. Song of Myself first appeared, untitled, in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ); it was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves.
- [Light and air!], about 1855; duk.00260; xxx.00048; MS 4to 4; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript draft of ideas related to section 31 in the final version of Song of Myself, which first appeared, untitled, in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ); it was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves.
- [I know as well as you that Bibles are divine revelation], about 1855; duk.00051; xxx.00048; MS 4to 5; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript draft treating ideas about divine revelation related to section 41 in the final version of Song of Myself, which first appeared, untitled, in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ); it was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves. The verso contains notes about the character and physical traits of several different men: Bill Guess, Peter, and George Fitch, dated March 20th '54.
- [(Fa)bles, traditions, and], Between 1850 and 1855; duk.00261; xxx.00048; MS 4to 6; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript draft with ideas and language related to what eventually became section 41 of Song of Myself and to the untitled fourteenth poem of the 1860 cluster Debris. Song of Myself first appeared, untitled, in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ); it was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves.The verso contains prose which begins "It is the endless delusion of big and little smouchers" and deals in part with the poor.
- [There is no word in any tongue], about 1855; duk.00018; xxx.00048; Trent II-7, 201; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript draft of ideas about God and man related to what eventually became sections 48-49 of the final version of Song of Myself, which first appeared, untitled, in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ); it was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves. This manuscript has been mounted and framed with a prose fragment, dealing with the soul and nature, and a photograph of Whitman. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- [My Spirit sped back to the], about 1855; duk.00262; xxx.00048; MS 4to 7; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript draft related in general to ideas expressed in Song of Myself, which first appeared, untitled, in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ); it was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves. The verso contains one cancelled line: "Not one of the heroic guests."
- Broadaxe, about 1856; duk.00033; xxx.00116; II-5 12; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes written in three separate columns about the uses and history of the broadaxe. The Broad-Axe Poem first appeared in Leaves of Grass ( 1856 ), taking the title Song of the Broad-Axe in 1867.
- [Poem (subject)], about 1873; duk.00047; xxx.00118; MS 18; poetry 3 leaves handwritten
  Notes for a poem about calls used in various occupations and, on the reverse of the second leaf, an early draft of a portion of Song of the Redwood-Tree, a poem first published in the February 1874 issue of Harper's Magazine and reprinted in the Centennial Songs section of Two Rivulets ( 1876 ). Verso images are not available for the first and third leaves.
- [I see who you are], about 1855; duk.00263; xxx.00119; MS 4to 8; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Lines, cancelled with a vertical strike, expressing ideas modified considerably before use in the third poem of the 1855 Leaves of Grass, later titled A Song for Occupations. On the verso is one heavily corrected line whose relationship to the recto material or to any other published poem is uncertain.
- [Perfect serenity of mind], about 1855; duk.00044; xxx.00115; MS 4to 194; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A fragment of several lines, apparently written before publication of the first edition of Leaves of Grass in 1855. One of the lines was included in the 1860 Poem of Joys, which was later entitled A Song of Joys.
- [This is the Earth's word], about 1856; duk.00019; xxx.00120; MS 4to 193; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A note possibly related to the poem A Song for Rolling Earth, first published in Leaves of Grass 1856. A portrait of Whitman accompanies this manuscript in the Trent Collection, however, an image of this portrait is not included in this finding aid.
- [Proem], about 1856; duk.00020; xxx.00047; MS 12mo 15; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  These notes on sights in Manhattan and the themes of personality, egotism, and the equality of women may have contributed to what ultimately became Starting from Paumanok, Section 12. The poem first appeared in the 1860 edition as Proto-Leaf.
- [O Mother, did you think], about 1856; duk.00034; xxx.00229; xxx.00052; MS 4to 13; poetry 4 leaves handwritten
  On four leaves, an early version of portions of the poem ultimately titled This Compost, first printed under the title Poem of Wonder at The Ressurection of The Wheat in the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass. On the reverse sides of these leaves is a list of words regarding the physical body and connected in concept to I Sing the Body Electric, a poem that first appeared as the fourth poem of the 1855 Leaves of Grass. With this list, Whitman was gathering material for the noteworthy final section, a paean to body parts, that he added to the poem in 1856. Glue residue shows that these leaves were formerly pasted to two other leaves, upon which is written a prose manuscript fragment regarding California Vigilance Committees.
- [To be at all], before 1855; duk.00001; xxx.00048; MS 4to 2; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  On one side are draft lines for what became section 27 of Song of Myself, which was first published as the opening poem in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. In 1897, after Whitman's death, a poem entitled To Be at All, based on this manuscript, was published in Old Age Echoes. On the reverse side are notes, trial lines, and lists of words and phrases related to what eventually became sections 24 and 49 of Song of Myself and to the poem In Paths Untrodden, first published in 1860 as the opening poem of the Calamus cluster.
- [And when once they went far enough to see], between 1850 and 1860; duk.00003; xxx.00048; xxx.00231; MS 4to 1; poetry prose 2 leaves handwritten
  On one side of these manuscript leaves are drafts of lines for the opening poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass, ultimately titled Song of Myself, sections six and seven. The poem was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves. On the reverse are fragments of an unpublished prose piece that appears to represent an early draft of "Unnamed Lands," a poem published first in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. The material on the second leaf shares with that poem not only a close thematic similarity but also several of the same phrases.
- [And I have discovered them by night and by], between 1850 and 1860; duk.00006; xxx.00048; xxx.00231; MS 4to 1; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  The draft lines on one side of the manuscript leaf contributed to the opening poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. In the poem's final version, Song of Myself, these lines are found in section 48. The poem was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves. It is not known whether the prose on the leaf's reverse is related to any of Whitman's published work; however, physical and thematic similarities with [And I have discovered them by night and by], above, and [My tongue can never be content with harness], below, make a connection with the 1860 poem Unnamed Lands likely.
- [My tongue can never be content with harness], between 1850 and 1860; duk.00008; xxx.00048; xxx.00231; MS 4to 1; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  On one side of the manuscript leaf are draft poetic lines with an unknown relation to Whitman's published work. However, physical and thematic similarities with [And when once they went far enough to see] and [And I have discovered them by night and by], above, suggest that the lines were possibly drafted for the 1855 poem that eventually became Song of Myself. These similarities also suggest that the prose on the leaf's reverse is likely related to Unnamed Lands, first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1860 ).
- Hands Ro[und], between 1865 and 1881; duk.00024; xxx.00607; MS 4to 24; poetry 2 leaves handwritten
  A manuscript poem with a patriotic theme left unpublished in Whitman's lifetime.
- [I am not content now], about 1855; duk.00026; xxx.00615; II-7 200; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript of two lines unpublished in Whitman's lifetime. An image of the verso is not available.
- [I am that halfgrown angry boy], before 1855; duk.00027; xxx.00616; MS 4to 25; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Poetry manuscript left unpublished by Whitman, containing ideas potentially connected with the unpublished short story [Of a summer evening]. On the verso is a fragment of an essay regarding municipal legislation.
- Poem of Existence, about 1860; duk.00060; xxx.00599; MS 4to 26; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript of poetic lines unpublished in Whitman's lifetime.
- [Remembrances I plant American ground with], Between 1850 and 1860; duk.00029; xxx.00001; MS 4to 27; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript containing ideas which appear frequently in Leaves of Grass. On the verso is a list of rivers, lakes, and cities.
- [Scantlings], about 1855; duk.00061; xxx.00609; MS 4to 202; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript containing ideas about a race of scantlings, a product of "the strong growth of America." Written on a scrap of the paper cover stock used for some late copies of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass; however, the connection of this manuscript to Whitman's published work is unknown.
- [Thought], about 1856; duk.00062; xxx.00617; MS 4to 28; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript left unpublished by Whitman containing draft ideas for a poem. Written on a sheet from the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- The most Jubilant Triumphant Poem, 1860 or before; duk.00265; xxx.00618; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript with ideas for a poem meant to express different forms of "great jubilant glee." The connection between this manuscript and Whitman's published works is unknown. This fragment has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [Poem of a proud].
- [Poem of a proud], before 1861; duk.00266; xxx.00619; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript with ideas for a poem of "joyous expression" about Manhattan, of which the connection to Whitman's published work is unknown. This fragment has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with The most Jubilant Triumphant Poem. An image of the verso is not available.
- Poem of the Black Person, 1860 or before; duk.00267; xxx.00620; MS 4to 29; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript with ideas for a poem expressing the "sentiment" of a "sweeping... protection of the blacks." It seems that no such poem ever emerged.
- Poem [There can be no greatest], 1860 or before; duk.00268; xxx.00621; MS 4to 29; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes toward a poem comparing the progress of "the divine man" to the geological development of the earth, of which the connection to Whitman's published works is unknown.
- Poem of Poets (now) in all lands, 1860 or before; duk.00269; xxx.00622; MS 4to 29; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript with notes for a poem to describe "the poetical sentiments in all lands," of which the connection to Whitman's published work is unknown. This fragment has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Poem (bequeathing to others a charge) what poems are wanted.
- Poem (bequeathing to others a charge) what poems are wanted, 1860 or before; duk.00270; xxx.00623; MS 4to 29; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript with idea for a poem to include "a long list" drawn from other (unidentified) manuscript scraps. This fragment has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Poem of Poets (now) in all lands. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- [And there a hunter's camp], about 1860; duk.00271; xxx.00114; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten